In this video, we will be starting optics
by
analyzing light and its formulae.
So, first of all, what is light? Light is
a
type of electromagnetic wave, and that
means
that it is coupled with electric and
magnetic
fields that travel through space. And it
doesn't
need a medium to travel in, so it can
travel
through a vacuum and it can travel in
anything.
That's why when you see in space, the sun
can
radiate light through space through a
vacuum
onto our earth. Now, an electromagnetic
wave
consists of an oscillating electric field
and
an oscillating magnetic field. So, E and
B,
where E is an electric field, and B
is a magnetic field. Now, these are
perpendicular
to each other. So, that means that if we
have
a ray of light going to, let's say, the
right,
then if our electric field is looking like
this,
then our magnetic field will be
perpendicular,
and it will look something like this. You
can
imagine it as a 3D diagram, where this is
a
right angle, the electric field is
vertical,
and the magnetic field is lying flat
perpendicular
to it. And a good fact to know is that
light
travels at 3.00 times 10 to the power of 8
metres
per second in a vacuum.
And this is really good to know.
You probably have learned this. But what
you
probably have not learned, that we will
cover
in this video, is that when light enters a
material,
such as glass and water, it slows down,
because
the interaction with the materials
actually
delays the light.
So, the formula is given as the speed of
light
is equal to the speed of light in a vacuum
over
n, which is the index of refraction.
Now, the index of refraction is basically
governing
how fast light can move in a constant.
The bigger the index of refraction means,
the
slower the light can be, and it is always
at
least one. This is because if it's less
than
one, then the speed of light will be
bigger
than that in a vacuum, which is not
possible.
Light has a wavelength as well, because it
also
behaves as a wave. Light is actually made
up
of photons, and it goes like a wave, so it
behaves
as something we call a wave-particle
duality.
So it can behave both as a wave and as a
particle.
And light, like any other wave, it has a
wavelength,
lambda, it has a frequency, it has a
period,
and it has an amplitude.
So, this connects to the wave equation,
where
v is equal to f times lambda.
Frequency times wavelength would be the
speed
of the light. And in a vacuum, v equals c,
because
the index of refraction is one. So, c
equals
frequency times lambda in a vacuum.
And this is really, really important,
because
this basically tells us that in a given
medium,
frequency stays the same, but wavelength
changes
when speed changes. So frequency always
stays
the same as long as it's the same
particle,
but wavelength can change when speed
changes.
Now, let's list the main behavior of light
and
explain what they mean.
First of all, the first behavior we'll be
analyzing
is reflection. And this basically says
that
light bounces off a surface. And for a
smooth
surface, the angle of incidence is
equal to the angle of refraction. You
might
have heard this in grade 10 science or in
your
extracurricular, but basically when we
bounce
off a smooth surface, let's say glass,
this
angle theta, let's call this theta i for
angle
of incidence, is equal to theta r, which
is
angle of refraction. And these are
measured
from the normal. This is the normal. The
normal
is basically an imaginary line that is
perpendicular
to the surface. Now, refraction.
Light changes direction when it enters a
new
medium, and this is what we will probably
be
focusing on in most of our high school
physics.
And it's basically governed by one
equation,
and that is called Lenz's law. Sorry,
Snell's
law. Snell's law. And basically
for refraction, the tools you will need is
the
normal. The normal, always try to identify
normal when doing these types of
questions.
And it is given by n1 sine theta 1 equals
n2
sine theta 2.
Basically, this says that, let's say we go
from
air into water, like a glass, a glass of
water,
and you shoot a beam of light, like for
example
a flashlight, and let's analyze one beam
of
light. If the light enters such that it
looks
like this, then we need to first identify
the
normal. The normal will be this.
This will be the normal. And since water
has
a higher index of refraction than air,
then
that means that n2 will be higher.
And so then theta 2 will be lower.
So that means it's going to go towards the
normal.
So it's going to look something like this.
And
then you do the same thing again. You draw
this.
Now it's going to bend away from the
normal.
So it's going to go like that.
And that's basically how light behaves in
a
glass of water. So what this can tell us
is,
as a rough estimate without calculations,
is
that a higher index of refraction, higher
n,
means that the light bends towards the
normal. Normal, oops, normal,
and vice versa. So when we have a higher
index
of refraction and we draw the normal, it's
going
to bend towards the normal and vice versa.
Now, the last property of light that we'll
be
analyzing in this unit is refraction.
Sorry, diffraction. Those are two
different
things. Diffraction. And this is how
light behaves when it's passing through a
narrow
slit or edge. And this is probably the
most
experimental unit of light we will go
through.
And I'll be talking more about that in
another
video. Now, one last thing before we end
off
this video is I want to talk about the
energy
of light. Light also has energy because
light
is photons and photons carry energy.
Energy, oops, energy of a light, of a
photon,
is given by H times frequency, where H is
a
constant, otherwise known as Planck's
constant.
It's probably given in your IB booklet if
you're
doing IB or AP. F is the frequency.
Since frequency stays the same in any
medium,
the energy of a photon stays the same in
any
medium as well. And this basically tells
us
that higher frequency light carries more
energy.
That's why gamma rays are way, way, way
stronger
than infrared, because the frequency is
really
way higher than infrared.
So, ultimately, this unit will be
analyzing
everything about light. We'll be analyzing
refraction,
optics, refraction, diffraction, and also
even
properties of its waves, such as
interference
and more diffraction.
And, yeah, this is a really fun unit, and
I
hope you will enjoy this as much as I do.
Thank you!